Guide to the Wallace Fowlie Papers, 1939-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Wallace Fowlie papers 1939-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Fowlie, Wallace, 1908-1998
1.0 Linear Feet 400 Items
Writer, critic, translator, and faculty member at Duke University specializing in modern French literature.
The Wallace Fowlie Papers span the years 1936 to 1998 and consist mainly of correspondence sent to Fowlie, but also publications on French literature authored by Fowlie, typescript and handwritten drafts by Fowlie, amd clippings pertaining to Fowlie's career. A significant portion of the correspondence comprises exchanges between Fowlie and Thomas and Kit Foster. These letters mainly address personal and family matters (health issues, vacations and meeting with mutual friends), but also cover projects Fowlie was working on, teaching positions accepted and rejected and class progress, and other matters of professional relevance. There is also a folder of correspondence with Fowlie, almost entirely in French, that was maintained by John M. Dunaway, a Romance Languages professor at Mercer College in Georgia. It includes a few color photographs. Other smaller amounts of correspondence come from Robert Heslen, a former student of Fowlie, and well-known writers/artists including René Char, Jean Cocteau, André Gide, Alexis Léger (Saint-Jean Perse), Marianne Moore, Anaïs Nin, and others, discussing literary matters and their writings and careers. A folder of general correspondence contains single letters from a variety of colleagues and friends.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Wallace Fowlie Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1981-2007, 2011.
Biographical Note
1908, Nov. 8 Wallace Fowlie born in Brookline, Massachussetts
1936 Received Doctorate from Harvard University
1943 Publication of Clowns and Angels: Studies in French Literature
1946 Rimbaud, the Myth of Childhood published
1951 Pantomime: A Journal of Rehearsals published
1953 Publication of Rimbaud's Illuminations
1964 Fowlie appointed to faculty at Duke University
1965 Publication of André Gide: His Life and Art
1966 Publication of Rimbaud (Complete Works) and Jean Cocteau: The History of a Poet's Age
1951 Duke Press published A Journal of Rehearsals, a revision and updating of the earlier 1951 autobiography, Pantomime: A Journal of Rehearsals
1983 Aubade: A Teacher's Notebook published
1984-1985 Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholar at nine universities and colleges
1987 Sites: A Third Memoir published
1990 Memory: A Fourth Memoir published
1990 Worked as consultant on Oliver Stone's film The Doors
1994 Publication of Rimbaud and Jim Morrison: The Rebel as Poet
1998, August 16 Died in Durham, North Carolina
Collection Overview
The Wallace Fowlie Papers span the years 1936 to 1998 and consist mainly of correspondence sent to Fowlie, but also publications authored by Fowlie, typescript and handwritten drafts by Fowlie, newspaper and newsletter article clippings pertaining to Fowlie, and other assorted printed material. A significant portion of the correspondence comprises exchanges with Fowlie and Thomas and Kit Foster, close friends of Fowlie. These letters mainly address personal and family matters (health issues, vacations and meetings with mutual friends), but also cover projects Fowlie was working on, teaching positions accepted and rejected, and class progress, and other matters of professional relevance. There is also a folder of correspondence with Fowlie, almost entirely in French, that was maintained by John M. Dunaway, a Romance Languages professor at Mercer College in Georgia. It includes a few color photographs. Other smaller amounts of correspondence, much of which is in French, come from Robert Heslen, a former student of Fowlie, and well-known writers, artists, and poets including René Char, Jean Cocteau, André Gide, Alexis Léger (Saint-Jean Perse), Marianne Moore, Anaïs Nin, and others, discussing French literature, their writings and careers, and Fowlie's writings. A folder of general correspondence contains single letters from a variety of colleagues and friends.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Fowlie, Wallace, 1980-1998
Char, René, 1907-1988
Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963
Dunaway, John M., 1945-.
Foster, Thomas
Gide, André, 1869-1951
Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972
Nin, Anaïs, 1903-1977
Authors, American -- 20th century
College teachers -- United States
French language -- 20th century
French literature
French poetry
Clippings
Color photographs
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1939-1998 and undated, (2 boxes)
  Chiefly consists of exchanges between Wallace Fowlie and well-known writers and friends. With the exception of the Foster and Heslen correspondence, which contains letters from Fowlie, the bulk of the items are from correspondents writing to Fowlie. Substantial groups of correpondence from individuals have been foldered separately. Smaller amounts of one to four letters are housed in General Correspondence; correspondents include Alain Bosquet, Kenneth Burke, René Char, Edouard Dermit (the adopted son of Jean Cocteau), André Gide, Marianne Moore, Jean Renard, and others. Arranged in chronological order within folders, with the exception of General Correspondence, which is alphabetical by last name.
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1951-1963 (Box 1)
  - Dunaway, John M., 1965-1998 and undated, (2 folders)
  - Foster, Thomas and Kit, 1945-1996 and undated, (8 folders)
  - Heslen, Robert, 1947-1957 and undated
  - Léger, Alexis, 1951-1965 and undated (Box 2)
  - Nin, Anaïs, 1945-1966 and undated
  - General correspondence, 1939-1970 and undated
- Printed Material Series, 1953-1979 and undated, (2 folders)
  - Printed material (Box 2)
    Contains various printed materials, including clippings, a publisher's catalog, writers' conference program, newsletter, project description, and a bibliography that was associated with correspondence to and from Thomas and Kit Foster. The clippings consist of newspaper and newsletter articles about Fowlie, some in interview format, that address his past and contemporary perspectives on literature and academia.
- Writings, 1949-1977 and undated, (7 folders)
  Consists of a small assortment of drafts and published versions of literary and biographical writings of Wallace Fowlie.
  - Journal of Rehearsals (typed draft with corrections), 1977, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Literary essays by Fowlie separated from R. Heslen correspondence, 1950, 1952
  - Literary essays and a translation by Fowlie separated from Thomas and Kit Foster correspondence, 1949, 1952, 1955, and undated
  - Notebooks, undated
    Consists of two spiral-bound notebooks containing Fowlie's hand-written drafts of literary essays.